Guide to the NYU Abu Dhabi Capstone Archives AD.MC.004
NYU Abu Dhabi, Archives and Special Collections
- Social Sciences Division Projects, 2014-2021
  - Political Science
    - Ebeze, Odera Chiamaka. Precolonial Political Centralisation, Education and Coethnic Voting, 2019; 2019-0181 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0181)
      While some existing literature has highlighted the impact of precolonial ethnic and political institutions on the long-term economic development of a country, research into the possible effects of these precolonial political institutions on ethnic voting on the African continent is scarce. For the purpose of this research, I will be looking primarily at the effects of precolonial political centralisation levels on coethnic voting for a presidential candidate. My secondary variable of study will be levels of education. Linking together literature and data on precolonial centralisation in Nigeria, Ghana, and Uganda, and individual levels of education, I find a strong positive association between my centralisation variable and coethnic voting. The long-run effects of precolonial institutions, however, do not appear to be driven by clientelist relationships of trust toward a traditional leader or belief that a leader should help his own community. Some evidence, however, shows that this relationship could be driven by norms of respect towards authority. An interaction between my centralisation and education variables overall shows that centralisation matters more than education though these differences are small.
    - Estes, Jocilyn. Confucius Institutes in the United States: Crouching Tiger or Hidden Dragon?, 2019; 2019-0141 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0141)
      World powers tend to export their ideals and agendas to mold the international status quo. The soft power methods that China utilizes to establish influence in other countries align with the idea of its peaceful rise. One instrument of this soft power strategy is the Confucius Institute program. These institutes are cultural and language centers at universities around the world, run and subsidized by the Chinese government. Research has suggested that increasing investment in public diplomacy programming through Confucius Institutes represents an attempt at establishing influence overseas in a non-confrontational manner. Others maintain that institutes constitute a national security threat by targeting universities that conduct dual-use research. This study examines a novel dataset of over 2,000 university-level observations including both Confucius Institute host and non-host institutions in the U.S. It finds that universities with large Science and research programs, and large enrollments are more likely to host institutes. As the first empirical research aimed at assessing the strategy behind Confucius Institutes in the U.S., this project acts as a preliminary examination of an ascendant power's informal diplomatic activities with citizens of a rival.
    - Ismail, Donia. Political Changes and Piety: Religion as Public Discourse in Urban Egypt, 2019; 2019-0177 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0177)
      In the Arab Middle East, the prevailing assumption is that religion shapes politics. Questions relating to the capacity of political changes to trigger various religious sentiments are often overlooked. This is especially true within Political Science scholarship. Through this project, I aim to answer one fundamental question: what are the effects of political shocks on religiosity amongst urban Egyptians? Observing this relationship in the specific context of Egypt allows me to interrogate the fluidity of the boundary between religion and politics. The events of the Iranian Revolution, the first Gulf War, the Invasion of Iraq, the Arab Spring and the Coup d'état represent the political shocks of interest. I then test for the effects of these shocks in relation to an observable element of religiosity: the figure of the veiled woman. By examining the veiling trends collected on one popular women's magazine, this capstone contributes to the construction of a time-series on the evolution of religiosity. Despite the absence of statistical significance for some findings, the overall study demonstrates evidence that counter the linear narrative attached to religiosity in Egypt.
    - Johnston, Maria Caeli. Political Engagement in Europe: What Groups of Voters are More Interested in Politics and Inclined to Trust Politicians?, 2019; 2019-0178 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0178)
      This paper looks at groups of voters that are more interested in politics and trusting towards politicians based on their domicile and educational attainment. Precisely, the paper offers literature overview that argued that interest in politics and political trust are important in determining the levels of political participation and, in the context of a current political movement, the effects of populism. The study uses these two variables - interest and trust - along with recent studies of voting behavior, to determine which groups of voters are likely to be participating in elections and effectively targeted by populist leaders. Regression analysis of the survey data from the European Social Survey offers following interpretation: people from rural areas are less likely to be interested in politics, and less likely to report trust in politicians. There is a positive relationship between the level of educational attainment and interest in politics, as well as between education level and trust in politicians. In conclusion, the paper suggests that when discussing determinants behind voting behavior that favors populism, it is important to consider what makes people more interested in politics and trusting towards politicians. Understanding voters' preferences and what political movements resonate with different voting groups, sparking their interest and trust is key to a successful political movement.
    - Karasira, Faustine. The effect of Performance contracts on Maternal and Child health services in Rwanda, 2019; 2019-0192 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0192)
      This paper examines the effect of performance contracts (Imihigo) on health services in Rwanda. I analyse how the introduction and the implementation of performance contracts has affected maternal and child health service delivery. This research paper contributes to available studies of the relation between performance contracts and the public sector, specifically the public health sector. I use difference-in-difference model and linear regression to estimate the effect of the introduction of performance contracts on individual level health outcomes. To do so, I use data from the Demographics Health Surveys (DHS) between neighbouring districts (South western) Uganda and (Northern) Rwanda to examine the difference in outcomes between these groups before and after the implementation of performance contracts in Rwanda. I expect to find that the introduction of performance contracts has positively impacted maternal and child health outcomes in Rwanda.
    - Lepp, Mari-Ann. The influence of i-voting on voter turnout: evidence from Estonia, 2019; 2019-0195 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0195)
      The motivation of this Senior Thesis is to understand the success of i-voting, along with future trends and possible weaknesses of the current system. The aim is to expand literature on existing alternative voting methods, especially internet voting, offering a case study of Estonia. This research paper explores the impact i-voting has had on political participation in Estonia, moreover it aims to examine whether all social groups benefit from i-voting mechanism similarly. I find that i-voting does have a positive impact on overall turnout rates. Concurrently, this paper reveals that Estonians systematically use i-voting more compared to non-Estonians, however, rural communities in Estonia do not utilize i-voting as expected and stated in the hypothesis. This study calls for further research in i-voting mechanism as it appears to benefit certain groups, and thus yields mixed results.
    - Madataly, Ifran. How did the 2015 Nigerian elections affect ethnic identification in Nigeria?, 2019; 2019-0163 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0163)
      Election periods have been strongly correlated to high ethnic identification in empirical analyses (Posner, Eifert, Miguel 2010). The 2015 Nigerian elections does not conform to theories from previous studies. The shift in voter preference between the 2011 and 2015 national elections could be explained by a shift from ethnic attachment towards national identification. Therefore, in this paper we explore the rise of national identification as an explanation to the fall in ethnic attachment. Firstly, we reexamine the role of elections, measured by its proximity and competitiveness on ethnic identification. Secondly, we assess the amplification of national identification by looking at the extent citizens positively perceive their country. Lastly, we evaluate the role of the media in reducing ethnic attachment. We find that the rise in national identification leads to the fall in ethnic identification. The increased access to news from the media improves citizens' political knowledge which stimulates the reduction of ethnic political preference and furthermore ethnic identification. These results contradict previous research and justifies the reasons why Nigerians did not identify to their ethnic identities in periods approaching the 2015 elections.
    - Mao, Xinyi. Examining the incentives of joining the Chinese Belt and Road Initiative, 2019; 2019-0155 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0155)
      The Belt and Road Initiative (BRI) is a multilateral cooperation framework proposed by China in 2013 to further economic, political and cultural exchanges. This paper explores the incentivizing and deterring factors that influence a country's decision to join the Belt and Road Initiative. Economic dependence in the form of reliance on foreign military aid, investments, and trade are found to increase political compliance to dominant countries' preferences. Voting patterns in the United Nations General Assembly are also found to be correlates of previous foreign aid and investments. Analyzing project-level Chinese foreign direct investment data prior to the BRI's inception, I find that Chinese investments motivate BRI joining when they are heavily concentrated in extractive sectors, but delay BRI joining when the sectors are less extractive, suggesting the importance of sector-specific and project-level approach to studying the BRI. Although not significant, I also find that American air force aid contributes the most to deterring BRI joining. However, regressions run on average data of the years preceding countries' decisions to join the BRI do not find a similar effect.
    - Mariano, Kirk. An Analysis of China's Emerging Influence on the ASEAN Geopolitics, 2019; 2019-0133 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0133)
      Foreign direct investment and foreign aid have always been used by social scientists as influential determinants of other economic factors, or has been influenced by economic and political factors. Since there seems to be a disproportionate paucity of literature regarding economic factors being identified as determinants of political factors, this research come into play as a contribution to the existing literature. In this study, as I tried to analyze the emerging influence of China in the ASEAN geopolitics using the aforementioned variables, I attempted to explore the status quo using the case of China, the ASEAN, and the US. I have found that the influx of Chinese foreign direct investment and foreign aid into the ASEAN member countries are not viable determinants of the ASEAN countries' UN General Assembly voting agreement with China or voting disagreement with the US contrary to the suggested status quo. However, other variables such as the Obama Effect, GDP per Capita, Control for Corruption, and Population variables are the ones that registered statistically significant results.
    - Melville-Rea, Hannah. Parched and Impatient: How Living in Drought Shapes Australian Politics, 2019; 2019-0174 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0174)
      Experiencing a climate disaster could alter the way people vote on election day. Previous scholarship suggests that these jarring events may decrease the popularity of those in power and rally support for leaders advocating for compensation, as opposed to preparedness spending. By examining the past decade of rainfall and voting records at over 8,000 polling stations across Australia, this study investigates how voters from drought affected and unaffected locations have comparatively voted in the Australian federal elections. As the first piece of research that tackles the impacts of drought on elections in Australia, it serves as a case study to understand how the lived experience of climate variability may have political ramifications. Results suggest that those affected by drought tend to support parties advocating for disaster relief rather than parties aiming to enhance water management, particularly in rural areas. This could sway election outcomes towards representatives focused on retrospective drought compensation and, in turn, exacerbate the likelihood of future water shortages in Australia. More broadly, if those at the front-lines of climate impacts prioritize the short term, the onset of climate events could fail to signal democracies towards taking actions necessary to manage future climate disasters.
    - Oh, Sally. How Attitudes towards Co-Ethnic Groups Are (Not) Affected by Identity Salience and Information Correction Mechanisms: Evidence from South Korea, 2019; 2019-0162 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0162)
      Can present bias against co-ethnic groups be changed for the better through reminders of shared identity and corrections of information? This study examines the prospects of doing so by conducting a survey of 1,172 South Koreans residing in Seoul, administering treatments of identity salience and information correction, and gauging their bias towards ethnic Koreans in or from China, commonly referred to as Joseonjok. The results show that neither mechanisms achieve the positive effect of reducing bias. If anything, the mechanisms seem to slightly worsen respondents' negativity towards Joseonjok and even towards other co-ethnic groups.
    - de la Pena, Enrique Lopez. Perspective Taking to Reduce Implicit Homophobic Behavior in Mexico, 2019; 2019-0175 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0175)
      2,951 adult Mexicans took part in an online survey experiment disguised as a donation game. Players were presented with a scenario where they had 20 pesos and needed to decide how much of this money to donate to an environmental activist and how much to keep for themselves. Each peso donated to the activist would be donated to the WWF. Conversely, each peso they kept would be converted into a ticket for the raffle of an iPad. Before donating, however, they were randomly and unknowingly assigned into one of four groups: 1) the main control group, 2) a control group where the activist was described as openly gay, 3) a treatment group where he was described as openly gay and of foreign (white) ancestry, and 4) a treatment group where he was described as openly gay after participants completed a perspective-taking exercise that required them to imagine living with hardships that are common to LGBTQ people in Mexico. Although there was no evidence of implicit homophobic behavior in the sample, it was found that the perspective-taking treatment effectively increased generosity towards the openly gay activist. The white ancestry treatment had no effect on respondents.
    - Peng, Penelope. What's the Price of a Vote? Chinese Aid in Sub-Saharan Africa, 2019; 2019-0208 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0208)
      This paper addresses the discourse surrounding Chinese influence in Africa by exploring the relationship between Chinese aid and voting behaviour in the United Nations General Assembly. I analyse whether increased aid donations to a sub-Saharan African country results in a higher incidence of aligned voting in the UN. I further determine whether differing types of aid have differing levels of impact on voting, dependent on the level to which the aid is grant-based. I also situate Chinese aid within a wider aid network by controlling for the other major regional aid donor, the United States. Despite the dominant narrative of Chinese geopolitical motivation, I find that receiving Chinese aid has no influence on voting. In fact, I find that both the level of American aid received and the political freedom of that country are better predictors of how often a country will vote in line with China.
    - Plyska, Oleksandra. What explains the allocation of public resources in Ukraine? Pork-barrel politics or socio-economic development?, 2019; 2019-0207 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0207)
      Pork-barrel politics is common across the world's democracies. Previous studies suggest that the ruling political parties use their advantage in the parliament to allocate more state resources to their preferred constituencies. Moreover, the possibility to get reelected in the upcoming elections incentivizes MPs to allocate more resources during the election year. I highlight the relationship between the ruling parties in the parliament and state resources allocation in the context of a newly established democracy - Ukraine. I analyze two measures of the sub-national allocations of discretionary grants: at the electoral district and oblast levels. The findings suggest that the effect of coalition on subventions is positive and significant. Additionally, the president's party allocates more subventions than other parties in the parliament, but it does not have an independent effect from being in a coalition. The findings for political business cycles theory are mixed: there is a positive effect in allocations of subventions across all parties, however, the relationship between the coalition and subventions in the election year does not appear to be statistically significant.
    - Salazar, Miren Aguirre. To Pay or NATO Pay, 2019; 2019-0200 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0200)
      Previous studies on the North Atlantic Treaty Organisation have focused on finding theoretical and qualitative explanations to the imbalanced contributions, lacking a counterfactual for how much countries would dedicate to defence expenditure, should the alliance not exist. I examine NATO's expenditure trends, by calculating and comparing counterfactual gures to the actual military expenditures of member states. Results show that NATO membership has a convergence effect towards the NATO 2% of GDP threshold and is particularly salient in periods without external threats to the members. This finding is in line with the constructivist socialisation framework for international relations.
    - Turchetti, Giulia. Propaganda Effects on Voters: Evidence from Hungary, 2019; 2019-0185 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0185)
      Over the last decades, the impact of biased messages displayed by the mass media has become a growing concern worldwide, as nations all over the world have witnessed populist parties which propagate extremist statements gaining or retaining power. The literature is divided about the effects of exposure to political propaganda: do messages consistent with the mainstream media make us more polarized? Can messages inconsistent with the mainstream shift our attitudes? Through original survey research carried out in Hungary, this Capstone seeks to understand the aggregate effect of biased political messaging in an imperfect democracy. I find that short-term exposure to a randomly assigned biased message does not shift voters' attitudes or willingness to engage in political action significantly. There remains much research to be done about the heterogeneous effects of systematic exposure to propaganda.
    - Wheeler, Chris. Aid, Arms or Autocrats?: Explaining the Voting Preferences of Developing Countries at the United Nations, 2019; 2019-0131 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0131)
      Despite their continued effort to bargain collectively on behalf of developing countries, the G77 group at the United Nations consistently fail to coordinate their voting positions. With 134 of the UN's 193 member states, the G77 has the potential to dominate the UN General Assembly, but has become so disparate that many now question the logic of the group's existence moving forward. Using newly developed ideal point estimates, I analyse the predictors of G77 countries' individual voting preferences in the UN General Assembly, to understand what is causing the growing division and disunity among the group. I find that voting preferences for individual countries within the G77 are determined mainly by variation in democracy and human rights, providing new insight both into the dynamics of the UN General Assembly, and into cooperation among developing countries more widely.
    - Wilson, Abi. He Said, She Said: Gender-of-Interviewer Effects in Eastern Congo, 2019; 2019-0160 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2019-0160)
      In survey research, sensitive questions are notoriously vulnerable to biases that lead to inaccurate responses. The question I will seek to answer in this study is: What role does gender play in sensitive interviews in Central Africa? Using data from a randomized survey conducted in the DRC, I ﬁnd that respondents tend to indicate more support for gender equality to female interviewers than male interviewers. However, women are generally less likely to receive responses that report occurrences of gender-based violence than men. Pairing a respondent with an interviewer of the same gender has little to no eﬀect. My results support a causal link between survey responses and interviewer gender. I suggest that cultural context is a key component in understanding gender eﬀects on survey design. My ﬁndings have practical implications for producers and consumers of survey data from Central Africa and underscore the importance of considering cultural context when designing in-person surveys.
    - Al Murr, Amal. Women in the Workforce: The Case of the UAE, 2020; 2020-0159 (E-records AD-MC-004, Folder 2020-0159)
      A common global trend that is often studied around the world is the disparity between high female tertiary education rates and low female workforce participation. Although many scholars in the field have studied these effects globally, none have studied them in the context of the UAE. Interestingly enough, the effects of high education and lower workforce participation are more prominent in the UAE since most of the female population in the UAE is highly educated. Nevertheless, this large population of educated women is not represented in the workforce, which raises many questions; Why are Emirati women acquiring a higher education if they do not plan to enter the workforce? More importantly, what are the potential explanations for such a high education rate, yet an extremely low workforce participation rate? To answer these questions, this study will entertain three potential explanations derived from previous literature based outside the region including; Family/Culture, Resources, and Discrimination. Through the scope of these explanations, this study aims to contribute to the scarce literature on such topics in the UAE and the greater Gulf region.
      Author contributed keywords: women, workforce, UAE, education, university, family, culture, resources, discrimination